Finding Aid for St. Alfred's Episcopal Church, Oxford, Michigan, Records 1954-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Alfred's Episcopal Church, Oxford, Michigan, records 1954-1996
St. Alfred's Episcopal Church (Oxford, Mich.)
Administrative files, bishop's committee meeting minutes, correspondence, church financial records.
02106 Ba 2
2.3 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the church and came from the diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) in June 2000. Additional records were received in 2006.
The record group is open for research.
St. Alfred's Episcopal Church, located near Oxford, Michigan, was founded on July 4, 1954 by the Rev. Richard S. Emrich, Episcopal bishop of Michigan, to serve the Lake Orion and Oxford area. The Rev. Charles Braidwood was the presiding minister over this mission church of the Episcopal Church Diocese of Michigan, preaching at the first service held in an old chicken coop. Seventy members attended that meeting.
On October 28, 1956, the congregation participated in a groundbreaking ceremony for a new church building to be located on M-24 near Indian Lake Rd. The first service in the new building was held on June 30, 1957. The Abby of Hyde, in Winchester, England, gave a large stone from their 850 year old abbey to the small congregation as a dedication gift for their altar.
On October 18, 1977, a groundbreaking ceremony took place for a new 4,000 foot fellowship hall, which was completed on May 27, 1979.
The fellowship groups at St. Alfred's Episcopal Church include the Episcopal Church Women, the Altar Guild, the Choir, Church School, Youth Ministry, Prayer Groups, Youth Choir, Holy Tares, and Bible Study as well as Mother/Daughter Groups, Father/Son Groups, Bethel Bible Study, Coffee House for the Youth, and Nursery/Day Care Center. The Committees include the Bishop's Committee, the Building Committee, Finance, Stewardship, Faith and Worship, Christian Education, Building and Grounds, and Future Planning.
Around 1996, after about 42 years of service, the church dissolved.
The records of St. Alfred's Episcopal Church in Oxford, Michigan, consists of 2.3 linear feet of material. These include publications, administrative material, church laws and constitution, contracts, council meeting minutes, various organizations, history of the church, correspondence, and financial documents. The records are arranged into five series: Background, Administrative Files, Bishop's Committee Meetings, Correspondence, and Church Finances.
The records of St. Alfred's Episcopal Church in Oxford, Michigan, consists of 2.3 linear feet of material. These include publications, administrative material, church laws and constitution, contracts, council meeting minutes, various organizations, history of the church, correspondence and financial documents. The records are arranged into seven series: Background; Administrative Files; Bishop's Committee Meetings; Correspondence; Church Finances; Registers of Church Services; and Registers of Baptisms, Communicants, Burials, Marriages, etc.
Subjects:
St. Alfred's Episcopal Church (Oxford, Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Oxford.; Oxford (Mich.)--Church history.
Subjects - Visual Material:
St. Alfred's Episcopal Church (0xford, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Oxford.; Oxford (Mich.)--Churches.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series (0.4 linear feet) documents the church's history and its response to such issues as homosexuality and racism in addition to providing an overview of its mission and the activities of the people who attended. The series also includes photographs, clippings, and plans of the church and the surrounding land.
  - Mission
    - Information (Box 1)
    - Laws 1978-1993 (Box 1)
    - Responses to Issues 1969-1990 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Scrapbook of Photographs (congregation, church building) (Box 1)
    - Loose Photographs 1955-1956, 1985, 1990 (Box 1)
      (ground breaking for church and parish, missions, church building)
  - Clippings
    - Scrapbook of Clippings 1946-1971 (Box 1)
      (also includes scattered photographs)
    - Loose Clippings
      - About Church 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - Blueprints (Box 1)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series (0.5 linear feet) documents the various proceedings within the church. It includes the church directories of both the congregation and the committees, the church registry, a small collection of bulletins, resumes submitted by various pastors, a summary of a pastor evaluation, church publications, and a few meeting minutes from various committees.
  - Church Directory
    - Main Directory 1960-1990 (Box 1)
    - Committee Directory 1961-1988 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins 1954-1988 (Box 1)
  - Pastor Resumes 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Pastor Evaluation 1987 (Box 1)
  - Church Publications
    - Our Church Times, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Monthly Review
      - 1963-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1978-1982 (Box 1)
        (after 1979 name changed to King's Courier)
    - Various other newsletters 1961-1993 (Box 1)
  - Blank Forms (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Various Meeting Minutes 1962-1990 (Box 1)
    - Episcopal Church Women
      - Information (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes 1957-1982 (Box 1)
      - Treasurer Reports 1957-1962 (Box 1)
    - Altar Guild 1989-1991 (Box 1)
- Bishop's Committee Meetings
  The Bishop's Committee Meeting series (0.8 linear feet) documents the history and meetings of the bishop's committee. It consists of both the monthly meeting minutes and the annual meeting minutes from the church's beginning to its end. These give an overview of the church's leadership and the proceedings of the church.
  - Minutes
    - 1954-1961, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1967-1985, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986-1996, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Annual Minutes 1957-1996, 7 folders (Box 2)
    (missing dates 1958, 1960-1964, 1966-1967, 1984)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.2 linear feet) documents the correspondence between various people in the congregation. Letters include correspondence between pastor and congregation, secretary and congregation, people in the congregation, the diocese and the congregation, different committees and the pastor, different committees and the congregation.
  - 1956-1996, 7 folders (Box 2)
    (missing 1980)
- Church Finances
  The Church Finance series is about 0.2 linear feet and documents the financial situation of the church. This series includes the budget (both monthly and yearly), annual parochial reports, town and country grant forms, and other related material.
  - Budget 1961-1996, 6 folders (Box 2)
    (missing 1983)
  - Parochial Reports 1954-1996, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (missing dates 1958-1962, 1964, 1967, 1974)
  - Town and Country 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Insurance Policy 1982-1988 (Box 2)
  - Contracts 1960-1988 (Box 2)
- Registers of church services
  - 1954-1963 (Box 3)
  - 1964-1974 (Box 3)
  - 1975-1989 (Box 3)
  - 1989-1997 (Box 3)
- Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages, etc.
  - 1954-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1995 (Volume 1)
    (marriages date to 1981 only)
  - 1981-1995 (Box 3)
    (marriage register only)